Guide to the Montana Power Company Predecessor Company records 1880-1947
Montana Historical Society
Montana Power Company Predecessor Company records
1880-1947
Montana Historical Society Archives
MC 268
Montana Power Company
200 linear feet of shelf space
Records (circa 1880-1947) of Montana Power Company predecessor companies consist of correspondence, financial records, legal documents, and minutes of many electric power, light, water, street railway, townsite, realty, and land companies around Western and Central Montana.
Historical Note:
The Montana Power Company was incorporated on December 12, 1912, as a result of a merger of the Butte Electric and Power Company, the Madison River Power Company, the United Missouri River Power Company, and the Billings and Eastern Montana Power Company. The merger was brought about by John D. Ryan, head of the Anaconda Copper Mining Company, and John G. Morony, president of the First National Bank of Great Falls. Each of the constituent companies had been formed as the result of mergers of earlier companies.
The Butte Electric and Power Company, was formed in 1901 to take over the assets and liabilities of the Butte Lighting and Power Company, which was, in turn, the successor to several local Butte power generating plants, including the Brush Electric Light and Power Company, the Silver Bow Electric Light Company, the Butte Electric Light and Power Company, the Silver Bow Electric Light and Power Company, the Butte General Electric Company, the Phoenix Electric Company, the Butte Gas Light and Coke Company, and others. The Butte Electric and Power Company's properties also included a hydro-electric power station on the Big Hole River from The Montana Power Transmission Company, successor to the Big Hole Improvement Company; and a majority interest in several Great Falls companies including the Great Falls Street Railway Company, the Boston and Great Falls Electric and Power Company, and the Great Falls Electric Properties.
The Missouri River Electric and Power Company, was organized in 1911, as a successor to the United Missouri River Power Company (UMRPC), which had gone into receivership. The UMRPC was itself a merger of the Missouri River Power Company, the Capital City Power Company, and the Helena Power Transmission Company. By 1912 the successor company owned most of the hydro-electric facilities on the Missouri River, including the first Canyon Ferry Dam completed in 1898 by the Helena Water and Electric Power Company; the Hauser Dam built in 1907 by the Helena Power Transmission Company; and the Holter Dam, begun around 1907 by the Capital City Power Company; and, due to financial difficulties, not completed until after the merger into Montana Power Company.
The Madison River Power Company was organized in 1905 by Butte Electric and Power Company interests to take over the Nunn power plant on the Madison River from The Power Company. The Madison River Power Company also constructed the Lower Madison Development in 1906 and transmission lines to Butte. In addition the Company acquired the Bozeman Electric Light Company, the Bozeman Street Railway Company, the Gallatin Light, Power and Railway Company, and the Livingston Water Power Company.
The Billings and Eastern Montana Power Company was organized in 1908 to take over various power developments along the Yellowstone River, including the Yegan Brothers properties, the Yellowstone River Power Company, the Billings Water Power Company, the Montana Trading Company, and the Big Timber Electric Light and Power Company.
After the organization of the Montana Power Company in 1912, the company continued to consolidate power developments around the state. In 1929 several major systems were acquired. The Missoula Public Service Company, was a merger of the Missoula Light and Water Company and the Missoula Street Railway Company both developed by William A. Clark. The various Helena properties which had been consolidated under the Helena Gas and Electric Company in 1927, also became part of Montana Power Company in 1929. A third major acquisition in 1929 was the Thompson Falls Power Company, including its predecessor the Northwestern Development Company. The Great Falls Townsite Company, the Great Falls Power Company, and the Great Falls Street Railway Company were all acquired by Montana Power Company between 1931 and 1936. The last major system acquired before World War II was the Union Electric Company of Dillon, which included the properties of its predecessors the Rife Electric Company and the Dillon Electric Light and Power Company. In addition, many local utilities were added for which there are no records in this collection.
[For more comprehensive information on the history of the predecessor companies see "Corporate Growth" [Box 1 Folder 2] and Douglas F. Leighton, The Corporate history of the Montana Power Company, 1882-1913, (M.A. Thesis. Montana State University, Missoula, 1951)]
Records consist of correspondence, financial records, legal documents, organizational records and other materials for the companies that made up the Montana Power Company, both before and after the organization of the Company. Records are arranged alphabetically by subgroup. The largest subgroups include:
Butte Electric and Power Company (1901-1912) records include interoffice and general correspondence, financial records, legal documents, maps, organizational materials, and reports.
Deer Lodge Electric Company (1892-1929) records include a historical information file, financial records, and organizational materials.
Great Falls Land Improvement Company (1905-1945) records include financial records and lot contracts. The Great Falls Power Company records include financial records concerning the construction of the Big Falls Development [Rainbow Dam], the Black Eagle Redevelopment, the Great Falls Development [Volta/Ryan], Holter Development, and Rainbow Extension; legal documents; and reports. Records of Great Falls Street Railway Company (1890-1936) include financial records and subject files. Records of the Great Falls Water Power and Townsite Company and its successor the Great Falls Townsite Company (1887-1936) include interoffice, incoming, outgoing, and general correspondence, employment records, financial records, lot books and other legal documents, organizational materials, and numbered subject files.
Havre Electric Company records (1904-1914) consist primarily of financial records and organizational materials.
There are records for several Helena companies which merged, separated and re-organized several times, including the Helena Electric Company, the Helena Electric Railway Company, the Helena Gas and Electric Company, the Helena Gas Light and Coke Company, the Helena Light and Railway Company, the Helena Motor Railway Company, the Helena Power and Light Company, the Helena Power Transmission Company, the Helena Steam Power and Lighting Company, the Helena Street Railway Company, the Helena Water and Electric Power Company, and others.
Records for the Lewistown Coal, Gas and Light Company and its successor the Lewistown Electric and Power Company (1907-1914) include historical information files, court papers, financial records, legal documents, and organizational materials.
The Madison River Power Company subgroup (1905-1912) includes a historical information file, incoming correspondence, financial records, legal documents, and organizational materials.
Records of the Missoula Light and Power Company and its successor the Missoula Light and Water Company (1896-1924) include incoming and outgoing correspondence, court papers, employment records, financial records, Public Service Commission hearings, legal documents, organizational materials, reports, and miscellany. The Missoula Street Railway Company records (1889-1927) include court papers, employment records, financial records, Public Service Commission hearings, legal documents, organizational materials, and miscellany, including accident reports. The Missoula Waterworks Company/Missoula Water Company subgroup (1886-1904) includes outgoing correspondence, court papers, employment records, financial records, and field books. In 1924 the various Missoula companies merged to form the Missoula Public Service Company. Records of this company (1924-1929) include court papers, employment records, financial records, and legal documents.
Records of the Missouri River Electric and Power Company (1912) include financial records, legal documents, and organizational materials. The Missouri River Power Company subgroup (1900-1910) includes general correspondence, financial records, legal documents, and organizational materials.
Records of the Montana Power Construction Company Milwaukee Road Electrification subgroup (1914-1916) include interoffice and general correspondence, employment records, and financial records of construction camps and outfit trains involved in the electrification of the Chicago, Milwaukee, and St. Paul Railroad. Records of the Phoenix Utility Company (1929-1934) include interoffice correspondence, financial records, and reports concerning the building of transmission lines and the Flathead and Morony hydro-electric projects.
The Thompson Falls Power Company subgroup (1912-1929) includes financial records, legal documents, and organizational materials.
Records of the Union Electric Company of Dillon (1908-1940) include general correspondence, financial records, legal documents, organizational materials, and reports.
Records of the United Missouri River Power Company (1906-1912) include a historical information file, court papers, financial records, legal documents, organizational materials, and reports.
There is a subgroup of Multi-company materials (1905-1927) which includes comparative financial statements for several companies, maps of transmission systems involving several companies, and statewide transmission line construction reports.
In addition there are papers for three company attorneys in Missoula: Walter M. Bickford, James M. Brown, and William L. Murphy. The Bickford papers are notable for including extensive correspondence with William A. Clark, William A. Clark, Jr., and Clark offices in Missoula and New York, many of a personal nature.
Arranged by subgroup and series. Some material housed in Oversize Boxes, Manuscript Volumes, and Archives Map Case. See inventory below for more information. NOTE: Volumes are not in numerical order.
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition information available upon request
MF 456 Montana Power Company Predecessor Company Records 1891-1936 includes material in microfilm foramt. See MF 456 finding aid for more information.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the Montana Historical Society Archives catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search under these terms.
Montana Power Company
Big Hole River (Mont.)--Barrages; Bitterroot River Valley (Mont.)--Commerce; Black Eagle Dam (Mont.); Bozeman (Mont.)--Commerce; Butte(Mont.)--Commerce; Canyon Ferry Dam (Mont.) [1st: 1896-1949]; Deer Lodge (Mont.)--commerce; Dillon (Mont.)--Commerce; Great Falls (Mont.)--Commerce; Hauser Dam (Mont.); Hebgen Dam (Mont.); Helena (Mont.)--Commerce; Holter Dam (Mont.); Lewistown (Mont.)--Commerce; Livingston (Mont.)--Commerce; Madison Dam (Mont.); Madison River (Mont.)--Barrages; Milltown Dam (Mont.); Missoula (Mont.)--Commerce; Missouri River--Barrages; Missouri River--Power utilization; Morony Dam (Mont.); Plains (Mont.)--Commerce; Rainbow Dam (Mont.); Rattlesnake Creek (Mont.); Ryan Dam (Cascade County, Mont.); St. Ignatius (Mont.); Spotted Bear (Mont.)
Boardinghouses--Montana.; Boats and boating--Montana.; Breweries--Montana.; Dams--Montana.; Dams--Montana--Design and Construction.; Electric power--Montana.; Electric power transmission--Montana.; Electric power plants--Montana.; Electric utilities--Montana.; Energy development--Montana.; Fish-culture--Montana.; Fisheries--Montana.; Fishing--Montana.; Floods--Montana.; Flour-mills--Montana.; Flumes--Montana.; Gas companies--Montana.; Hunting and fishing clubs--Montana.; Indian land scrip--Montana.; Industrial accidents--Montana.; Labor disputes--Montana.; Lieu lands--Montana.; Municipal Water Supply--Montana.; Natural gas--Montana.; Petroleum refineries--Montana.; Public utilities--Montana.; Railroads--Design and construction--Montana.; Railroads--Electrification--Montana.; Real estate business--Montana--Great Falls.; Reservoirs--Montana.; Street-railroads--Montana--Great Falls.; Street-railroads--Montana--Helena.; Street-railroads--Montana--Missoula.; Townsites--Montana--Great Falls.; Water-power--Montana.; World War, 1914-1918--Washington, D.C.
Montana; City Planning; Fisheries and Wildlife; Public Utilities; Railroads
Detailed Description of the Collection
The following section contains a detailed listing of the materials in the collection
- Montana Power Company Historical Background Material
  - Historical Material
    - "Brief history and development of the Montana Power Company and its subsidiaries", circa 1935 (Box-folder 1 / 1)
    - "Corporate growth" (history of all predecessor companies at time of formation of Montana Power Company and other material), circa 1912 (Box-folder 1 / 2)
    - "Events leading up to the formation of the Montana Power Company" by C.H. Kirk, 1942 (Box-folder 1 / 3)
    - "The Montana Power Company and subsidiaries: some significant historical dates", 1953 (Box-folder 1 / 4)
    - "Montana Power Company and subsidiary companies construction completed, 1915" (Box-folder 1 / 5)
    - Original cost of predecessor companies, 1942 (Box-folder 1 / 6)
    - Report by F.M. Kerr on history of power development in various communities, 1936 (Box-folder 1 / 7)
- Beaverhead Transmission Company
  - Financial Records
    - Cash book, 1922-1940 (Box-folder 1 / 8)
    - General ledger, 1923-1929 (Volume 1)
    - Journal, 1922-1940 (Box-folder 1 / 9)
    - Voucher register, 1927-1937 (Volume 2)
  - Organizational Records
    - Minutes, 1940 (Box-folder 1 / 10)
    - Stock certificates, 1922-1940 (Box-folder 1 / 11)
  - Subject File
    - Liquidation of company, 1939-1940 (Box-folder 1 / 12)
- Billings and Eastern Montana Power Company
  - Historical Material
    - Historical information file, undated (Box-folder 2 / 1)
  - Financial Records
    - Cash book, 1909-1915 (Volume 3)
    - Check register, 1910-1912 (Volume 4)
    - Construction expenditures [Oversize Box], 1908-1909 (Oversizebox 1)
    - Financial statements, 1910-1911 (Box-folder 2 / 2)
    - General ledger, 1908-1909 (Volume 5)
    - General ledger, 1909-1913 (Box-folder 2 / 3)
    - Journal, 1908 (Volume 6)
    - Transfer ledger, 1909-1912 (Box-folder 2 / 4)
    - Voucher registers, 1909-1914 (Volume 7-8)
    - Voucher registers: Big Timber Branch, 1909-1913 (Volume 9)
- Bitter Root Power and Electric Company
  - Legal Documents
    - Agreement with United States Forest Service and Missoula National Forest (re dams, reservoirs, conduit line, and power house), 1910 (Box-folder 2 / 5)
  - Reports
    - Report on Rock Creek Project, 1910 (Box-folder 2 / 6)
- Boston and Great Falls Electric Light and Power Company
  - Financial Records
    - General ledgers [continued in Great Falls Electric Properties subgroup], 1890-1908 (Volume 10-12)
    - Journal, 1901-1907 (Volume 13)
    - Voucher registers [volume 2 includes Great Falls Street Railway Company], 1901-1909 (Volume 14-15)
  - Organizational Records
    - Minutes, bylaws, etc., 1890-1909 (Box-folder 3 / 1)
- Boston and Great Falls Land Company
  - Financial Records
    - Details of cost sheets [3 folders; Oversize Box], 1894-1901 (Oversizebox 1)
    - Profit and loss statement, 1894 (Box-folder 3 / 2)
    - Trial balances, 1894-1901 (Box-folder 3 / 3-6)
  - Legal Documents
    - Lot contracts #1-239 [continued in Great Falls Land Improvement Company subgroup], 1891-1903 (Box-folder 3 / 7-8)
    - Miscellaneous (includes mortgages, deeds, foreclosure deed), 1893-1901 (Box-folder 3 / 9)
  - Miscellany
    - Miscellaneous (includes lot lists, plats), 1901-1910 (Box-folder 3 / 10)
    - Record of lots [arranged by block], 1891-1906 (Volume 16)
- Bowen Brothers Electric Light and Power Company
  - Organizational Records
    - Stock certificates, 1916-1931 (Box-folder 4 / 1)
- Bozeman Street Railway Company
  - Financial Records
    - Cash book, 1897-1908 (Box-folder 4 / 2)
    - General ledger, 1897-1908 (Box-folder 4 / 3)
    - Job book, undated (Volume 17)
    - Journal, 1897-1909 (Box-folder 4 / 4)
    - Miscellaneous record of equipment, circa 1903 (Box-folder 4 / 5)
    - Ticket record, 1897-1908 (Box-folder 4 / 6-7)
- Brush Electric Light and Power Company
  - Outgoing Correspondence
    - Letterpress copies, 1883-1886 (Box-folder 5 / 1)
  - Financial Records
    - General ledger, 1882-1886 (Volume 18)
    - Invoices: Rocky Mountain Electric Light Company, 1882-1886 (Box-folder 5 / 2)
    - Invoices: miscellaneous, 1883-1885 (Box-folder 5 / 3)
    - Journal, 1882-1886 (Volume 19)
  - Organizational Records
    - Record book (includes minutes, articles of incorporation, bylaws, etc.), 1882-1886 (Volume 20)
    - Stockholder ledger, 1884 (Box-folder 5 / 4)
- Butte Electric and Power Company
  - Interoffice Correspondence
    - Miscellaneous (correspondents include H.W. Turner, C.W. Wetmore, R.H. Ballard, P.E. Bisland, Copley Amory, John D. Ryan, Max Hebgen, stockholders), 1902-1912 (Box-folder 6 / 1)
  - General Correspondence
    - Miscellaneous (correspondents include Forbis and Mattison, J.L. Wines, Morley and Thomas, C.P. Allen, J.L. Templeman. S.Z. Mitchell, Coudert Brothers), 1902-1908 (Box-folder 6 / 2)
  - Financial Records
    - Audits, 1907-1912 (Box-folder 6 / 3)
    - Balance sheets and consolidated profit and loss statements, 1910-1911 (Box-folder 6 / 4)
    - Bonds, 1901-1908 (Box-folder 6 / 5)
    - Cash book, 1909-1911 (Volume 21)
    - Cash requirements and statement of resources, 1904 (Box-folder 6 / 6)
    - Estimate of earnings, power requirements and available power, 1911-1915 (Box-folder 6 / 7)
    - Financial history, 1901-1912 (Box-folder 6 / 8)
    - General ledgers, 1901-1908 (Volume 22-30)
    - General ledger, 1909-1912 (Box-folder 6 / 9-10)
    - General ledger (continued), 1909-1912 (Box-folder 7 / 1-2)
    - General ledger: gas, 1895-1906 (Volume 31-32)
    - General ledger: gas, 1909-1912 (Box-folder 7 / 3-5)
    - Journals, 1902-1910 (Volume 33-35)
    - Journal entries, 1905, 1912 (Box-folder 7 / 6)
    - Operating reports: monthly, 1908-1910 (Box-folder 8 / 1-5)
    - Operating reports: monthly, 1911-1912 (Box-folder 9 / 1-4)
    - Operating reports: yearly, 1908-1912 (Box-folder 10 / 1)
    - Requisition books, 1938-1939 (Box-folder 10 / 2-3)
    - Statistics, 1906-1915 (Box-folder 10 / 4)
    - Trial balances, 1909-1912 (Volume 36)
    - Voucher registers, 1904-1910 (Volume 37-40)
    - Voucher registers: gas branch, 1909-1912 (Volume 41-42)
    - Voucher register index cards, 1909-1912 (Box-folder Card / Box)
    - Miscellaneous (includes coal tests, pole line costs), 1901, undated (Box-folder 10 / 5)
  - Legal Documents
    - Agreement of consolidation forming Montana Power Company, 1912 (Box-folder 11 / 1)
    - Applications for arc and incandescent lights, 1901-1906 (Box-folder 11 / 2-6)
    - Applications for arc and incandescent lights, 1906-1908 (Box-folder 12 / 1-5)
    - Applications for arc and incandescent lights, 1908-1909 (Box-folder 13 / 1-6)
    - City of Butte building permits, 1905-1907 (Box-folder 14 / 1)
    - Contracts, specifications, etc.: Butte Division #9, 1910-1911 (Box-folder 14 / 2)
    - Contracts, specifications, etc.: Lower Madison Develpment #27, 1901 (Box-folder 14 / 3)
    - Contracts with F.A. Heinze (re franchises, Race Track power site), 1906-1907 (Box-folder 14 / 4)
    - "Franchises belonging to and under which Butte Electric and Power Company and subsidiary companies are operating in Montana", 1908 (Box-folder 14 / 5)
    - Lease from Missouri River Electric and Power Company, 1912 (Box-folder 14 / 6)
    - Mortgages (includes material on continuation of debt under Montana Power Company), 1901-1967 (Box-folder 14 / 7)
    - Miscellanous, 1897-1912 (Box-folder 14 / 8)
  - Maps
    - Maps and specifications: transmission system [Oversize Box], 1913 (Oversizebox 2)
    - Maps of properties and water power developments, 1911, undated (Box-folder 14 / 9)
  - Organizational Records
    - Certificate of incorporation and bylaws, 1901 (Box-folder 14 / 10)
    - Investment securities and stock ownership, 1901-1912 (Box-folder 14 / 11)
    - Lists of officers, directors and stockholders, 1890-1912 (Box-folder 14 / 12)
    - Minutes and excerpts from minutes, 1901-1912 (Box-folder 14 / 13)
    - Plan for organization of Montana Power Company, 1912 (Box-folder 14 / 14)
    - Purchase of Great Falls Water Power and Townsite Company, 1908-1909 (Box-folder 14 / 15)
    - Purchase of United Missouri River Power Company property, 1912 (Box-folder 14 / 16)
    - Stock and bond prices, 1906-1912 (Box-folder 14 / 17)
    - Stock receipt books: common [Oversize Box], 1901-1912 (Oversizebox 2)
    - Stock receipt books: preferred [Oversize Box], 1901-1912 (Oversizebox 3)
  - Reports
    - "Estimate of total amount of power which can be developed by the water power plants of Butte Electric and Power Company, Great Falls Power Company, United Missouri River Power Company and associated companies" by H.H. Cochrane, 1910 (Box-folder 14 / 18)
    - Report by John A. Cole, consulting engineer on property of Butte Power Transmission Company, 1902 (Box-folder 14 / 19)
    - "Report on Madison River", by Max Hebgen (includes photographs), 1905 (Box-folder 14 / 20)
    - "Preliminary Report on Power and Load Conditions, Missouri River System", by Max Hebgen, 1912 (Box-folder 14 / 21)
  - Subject File
    - Madison River Power Company and Madison River dam (includes correspondence, water right, M.L. MacDonald, M. Hebgen reports), 1901-1905 (Box-folder 14 / 22)
  - Clippings
    - "Butte Electric's Showing: Largest Earnings in Company's History during 1909" Wall Street Summary, January 1910 (Box-folder 14 / 23)
- Butte Electric Light Company
  - Miscellany
    - "Book of record" (lists names and addresses of customers, numbers of lights, inventory of equipment, etc.), 1892 (Box-folder 15 / 1)
- Butte Gas Light and Coke Company
  - Financial Records
    - General ledgers, 1890-1901 (Volume 43-44)
- Butte Gas Light and Fuel Company
  - Historical Material
    - Historical information file, 1902-1908 (Box-folder 15 / 2)
  - Financial Records
    - Trial balances, 1904-1912 (Volume 45)
  - Legal Documents
    - Customer applications #1-513, 1902-1905 (Box-folder 15 / 3-6)
  - Organizational Records
    - Minute book [Oversize Box], 1899-1904 (Oversizebox 3)
    - Bylaws, amendments, and proxies (removed from water-damaged volume), 1899-1904 (Box-folder 15 / 7)
    - Stock certificates, 1900-1908 (Box-folder 15 / 8)
- Butte General Electric Company
  - Historical Material
    - Historical information file, 1892-1899 (Box-folder 16 / 1)
  - General Correspondence
    - Miscellaneous, 1893-1899 (Box-folder 16 / 2)
  - Outgoing Correspondence
    - Letterpress books: H.W. Turner, 1897-1898 (Box-folder 16 / 3-4)
    - Letterpress copies (scattered), 1895-1898 (Box-folder 16 / 5)
  - Financial Records
    - General ledgers, 1892-1901 (Volume 46-49)
    - Journal [first 3 pages photocopied because they would not microfilm: moldy], 1892 (Box-folder 16 / 6)
    - Voucher register, 1892-1894 (Box-folder 16 / 7)
  - Legal Documents
    - Applications for arc and incandescent lights, 1892-1900 (Box-folder 17 / 1)
    - Miscellaneous, 1889-1899 (Box-folder 17 / 2)
  - Reports
    - "Report of the Butte General Electric Company", 1892-1896 (Box-folder 17 / 3)